Jess Dowd

Front End | Web Developer | Software Engineer

LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio | jessalyndowd@gmail.com | 1-573-245-2164 | MO, USA

Summary

Full-stack web developer proficient in HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Node, and React with a background in eCommerce. Transitioned from building e-commerce store and product development to web development to help companies make an impact in the ever-growing tech industry. I find an interesting crossover between my software and my business experience. Both pursuits challenge so many aspects of the intellect: creativity, organization, time management, sequential processing, problem-solving.

Technical Skills | Languages | Tools

HTML5 - CSS3 - JavaScript/JSX - React - CRA - SQL and jQuery - API - OOP - React components - React Hooks Algorithms - Continuous Integration (CI) - Data Structures - Deployment - Unit Testing Webpack - Babel - JSON - SQL - DOM - Debugging - SCSS - Form validation - Git/GitHub - Figma - NPM flexbox - grid layout - BEM - Media queries - transition - CSS Frameworks - Styled-Components English (Native), Thai (Basic, A2), Mandarin (Beginner, A1)

Technical Projects

Around the U.S - React - 07/2021 Website | Code files

Front-end App using API to fetch data, CSS and jquery to create adaptive layout and JSX, React CRA to add interactivity

- Built maintainable, reusable UI components using API and JS
- Successfully implemented webpack and Babel to increase load speed
- Recently moved the relevant codebase from jQuery/vanilla JS to React

Learning How to Learn - 02/2021 Website | Code files

Front-end App built with HTML and using CSS to create an interactive website on learning techniques

- Used CSS3 extensively to create seamless animation and hover effects
- Built reusable components using HTML, CSS, and BEM organizational methods

From Portland to Portland - 07/2020 Website | Code files

Front-end Application built with HTML and using CSS grid to display adaptive array of photos

- Used media queries to build a smooth UX/UI across all platforms (iPhone, Android, Tablet)
- Created pixel-perfect recreations of designer mock-ups from figma

See More.....

Experience

Freelance | Web Developer | 01/2021 - Current

- Design and build websites using technologies JSX, CSS, NextJs and ReactJS
- Built a personal website for a software engineer. Researched and improved overall site interaction and design by developing interactive and smooth UI/UX.
- Currently working on a web application for a nail salon client. Using react to create an app in which the user can reserve appointments.

English Teacher | Remote | 02/2020 - 04/2021

- Prepared and taught one-on-one English lessons to over 200 children aged 4-14.
- Adapted curriculum to maximize improvement for each individual student.
- Helped students prepare for the TOEFL exams.

Ecommerce WordPress | Manager - Jessential | 2013 - 2017

- Built e-commerce store, inventory management, product development, label and logo design,
- Increased business profits 33% yearly on average through continuous improvement of website and products
- Designed a efficient workflow and trained two contractors to take over shop management and customer service
- Directed and managed successful product launch from concept to deployment.

Education

Practicum by Yandex | Intensive Web Development bootcamp program | 2020-2021

- Completed 10 independent projects using languages HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JSX, JS frameworks, libraries like React, and industry best practice standards for clean code.
- Worked with classmates for two week long sprints in an agile environment and participated in code reviews with senior developers.
- Project-based course. The curriculum provides a wide range of projects based on current Full Stack Development technologies

Bachelor in Business Administration (B.B.A) | Burapha University online

- Global Business Administration and Finance
- Elected Major Leader of Finance for the class of 2020 GPA 3.75